<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lgsump.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lgsump.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-05-07T06:05:08+00:00</updated><id>https://lgsump.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Luke G. Sumpter</title><subtitle>Philosophy and History Student at the University of Texas at Austin
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Arrival</title><link href="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2023/arrival/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arrival" /><published>2023-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2023/arrival</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2023/arrival/"><![CDATA[<h4><i>Arrival</i> (2016), a Denis Villeneuve film, explores the role of time and our understanding of it in how it involves itself as a structure within our lives. We follow Dr. Louise Banks and her life after seemingly losing her daughter to a serious disease. In this short essay, we will point out different aspects of the film, some included in the commentaries in the clips shown before and some not, that realize some key points that Deleuze hinted to us but also give us more simplistic conceptions of the influence that time has on art and our perception of life. The film has now become a large centerpiece for philosophical and linguistic repertoires inside of Cinema. The beginning montage leads the audience to believe that the daughter of Louise had died and that we were there after seeing her role as a professor and linguist coming to terms with her daughter's death. We are led to believe that this movie was going to be about how even after her daughter’s death, her memory still lives on. In a surprise to many, as we uncover gradually throughout the film, Louise was receiving– or we were receiving– visions of the future due to her heightened ability to recognize the influence of language within her life. So, as Louise figures it out and begins to learn the language of the aliens, she becomes more and more able to see the future.</h4>
<p><br />
<br />
<br /></p>
<p style="text-align:center;"><img width="82" alt="Screen Shot 2023-03-12 at 6 49 48 PM" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/122332459/224581969-13c76853-e305-4e9a-b53e-9b2a3d31f5c1.png" /></p>
<h6><center>Picture from <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/pin/476959416790757876/">Pinterest.</a></center>
<br />
<br />
<h4>As shown above, the language of the aliens has a circular appearance and seems to also connect to this cyclical nature of time that Villeneuve is arguing. The previously shown montages are also in connection to this idea, as we see with the montage, in the beginning, coming back to us at the end of the film. An interesting idea behind this is that when thinking about the movie beforehand, realizing that something happened twice, like the use of montage, doesn’t necessarily relate those recurrences to the imagery of the circle. This distinction is interesting also through the use of “On The Nature Of Daylight” by Max Richter which plays throughout the montages, as we hear that two-note repetition. When we see these on a line, we see two separate and independent instances that feel more like rhythm than image. However, their imagery comes when recognizing that they are the same and aligning them with each other, pulling the two points on a line to create a loop.</h4>
<br />
<br />
<h4>As we saw through <a href="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2021/deleuze-and-time/">Deleuze’s discussion</a>, the montage itself is also a play of time and movement. Naturally, or unnaturally, montages show us an unrealistic representation of time. As we see in these two montages, the images and clips are not systematic in length, motion, or dialogue. Villeneuve seems to be connecting these ideas of time as a whole or cycle as well as viewing them as completely natural. Many distinctions made in the realm of digital art seem to criticize the function and world that these artworks develop and live in because of their distinct abstraction from nature. When we think of montages and edits of clips we often think that those decisions would guide the work away from the natural world and their natural course, but Villeneuve seems to be suggesting that these aspects of manipulation in these technological works like film give them the ability to transform these concepts much more accurately.</h4>
<br />
<br />
<h4>What films like <i>Arrival</i> allow us to see is that, in many ways, the abstraction of art into the technical world but still guided by that vision can still give a very authentic feel. Even though this film was systematically made and curated with close intention; even though it was filled with mountains of organizational and bureaucratic aspects; or even through its plethora of emails; the least we can get– if not the original artistic vision of Villeneuve and the confirmation once it has gone through the process– a very real and telling transformation that those ideas go through in the seemingly independent mind of human organization. In these aspects of transformation, and especially in this case how time itself is transformed, one can free themselves from the system that one was born into. We were given a world created by Villeneuve, and he then broke it in front of us. The art of the story is central to most forms of art and is especially integral to Film. <i>Arrival</i> shows us that our conception of time is important not only in the cliche and abstract landscape of our philosophy on life, but a very real and pertinent structure to the reality of a story. As we see in both the ending and beginning montages of the film, the idea of those concepts themselves, ending and beginning, is called into question and in some sense, destroyed.
</h4></h6>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Arrival (2016) analysis paired with Deleuze, an example from A Digital Florilegium.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deleuze and Time</title><link href="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/deleuze-and-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deleuze and Time" /><published>2022-12-06T12:30:12+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T12:30:12+00:00</updated><id>https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/deleuze-and-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/deleuze-and-time/"><![CDATA[<h4>Gilles Deleuze was a French philosopher who worked heavily in causality and aesthetic, literary, and film theory. This essay will focus on his two works on film, <i>Cinema I: The Movement-Image</i> and <i>Cinema II: The Time-Image</i>, published in 1983 and 1985, respectively.</h4>
<p><br />
<br /></p>
<p style="text-align:center;"><img width="302" alt="Screen Shot 2023-03-08 at 11 42 23 PM" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/122332459/223931379-30258981-ff66-4af0-83c9-7f8eda360e46.png" /></p>
<h6><center> Picture from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilles_Deleuze#/media/File:Gilles_Deleuze.webp">Wikipedia.</a></center>
<br />
<hr />
<h2>To check out this work along with its annotations and the project as a whole, go to the <a href="https://lgsump.github.io/projects/">projects page</a>, and it is titled <i>A Digital Florilegium</i>.
<hr />
<h4>In his major works on film, Deleuze combines film criticism and philosophy. While both are in many regards considered separate, Deleuze brings them together in these two books in a way that makes them seem indistinguishable. It is important to note that many of his ideas, like the terms Movement-Image and Time-Image, come from and through a critique of Henri Bergson’s theories on perception. These books are no exception, as he explicitly states in the books. As an introduction to Deleuze, the concepts of repetition and difference repeat, ironically, throughout most of Deleuze's work. <i>Difference and Repetition</i> (1968) is considered his magnum opus and lays the foundation for many of his works, including the two on Cinema. It represents the idea of difference <i>in</i> itself and repetition <i>for</i> itself, which are names of sections of the piece, which was also his principal thesis. These ideas are important to recognize with the role of memory in Deleuze's film theory that is about to be laid out. For this project's themes of transformation and time, we will look into how Deleuze understands the nature of film and its artistry, especially in how time and movement, or in our words, transformation, play with it at its very foundation. Our inspection of the relationship between modern film and digital art will require us to spend most of our <i>time</i> on the second book <i>Cinema II: The Time-Image</i> compared to the first. This is also because he goes more into where he talks about where he believes film should be heading. For clarity, which is seldom to find at first glance in Deleuze, we can see an integral part of his theory straight from his words in the second book:</h4>
<br />
<br />
<blockquote>“Hence a first thesis: it is a montage itself which constitutes the whole, and thus gives us the image of time. It is therefore the principal art of cinema. Time is necessarily an indirect representation, because it flows from the montage which links one movement-image to another.” (Deleuze 34, The Time-Image)</blockquote>
<br />
<h4>His understanding of a montage is as a determination of a whole in the way it is warped or represented through its sequence; how the different images or shots are cut, and the utility of false continuity. Those are similar to how we view montages now in some sense, as it is how we can use the clipping of images to represent a very long period, and in many ways, we can use this manipulation of time, or false continuity, to represent a different idea. The importance here is for his later introduction to where he believes Cinema should be heading, ideally, which is where the lines of movement should bleed and melt between the images and become a crystallized whole. We will see this also in the chapters on <i>Arrival</i> (2016). Something important to note in his discussion above through the connection of Movement-Images is that this quote doesn’t necessarily tell us anything about the good or bad aspects of the role of time in film. Deleuze merely points out that this relationship between time and film, as an art, and for us through his understanding of transformation from one to another, as a foundational aspect of the discipline. </h4>
<br />
<br />
<h4>Within the first book <i>Cinema I: The Movement-Image</i> and to establish context for our discussion of the second, Deleuze concludes with his discussion of images and the history of film by criticizing the obsession with movement as its pure self. This fixation on movement is where Deleuze believes the artist to be losing this human essence. This book highlights the material discussion of film and the utility and foundation of the concept of movement in film. However, many people, like Deleuze, believed that there was a need to move it further, or that there was something within the discussion itself that would allow for a more authentic experience. The Time-Image to Deleuze is beyond the Movement-Image by disconnecting the action and how we associate or sensualize those actions. To explain, it is when one isolates the sensation, like what one sees or hears, from the specific scene or situational image itself. That isolation, to Deleuze, reignites the authenticity of movement in film through its reinforcement in distinct durations. Moreover, when focusing on sensation or a specific part of a scene, there also seems to be a bit of contradiction to further aspects of his understanding of the Time-Image as we are led to believe that it is also an abstraction. This leads to confusion for many people because the question of: how can one get more specific as well as more abstract? He answers this through the explanation of the Crystal-Image.</h4>
<br />
<br />
<blockquote>“From this point of view, time depends on movement itself and belongs to it: it may be defined, in the style of ancient philosophers, as the number of movement. Montage will therefore be a relation of number, variable according to the intrinsic nature of the movements considered in each image, in each shot.” (Deleuze 35, The Time-Image)</blockquote>
<br />
<h4>Through this distinction of time through the 'number of movement', we begin to enter Deleuze’s solution to the cliché crisis of film. He believes the creation of the Time-Image will restore the authenticity of film, and we will argue through its extension in the other pieces of the project as an abstract version to restore the authenticity of all digital art. Deleuze continues to argue from this distinction the use of illusion and falsity regarding creation and novelty. This is where we get into the technical aspect of the Crystal-Image. The Crystal-Image is a depiction and unison of the real and the imaginary, the virtual and the actual, through the structuralization of time or non-chronological time. This specific understanding of time is important in that it expresses the seemingly paradoxical or false nature of time, though, in actuality, it also comes from an influence on Deleuze from Bergson on the split of time in habitual memory. To attempt a brief explanation of this dissonance, the very present-like nature of memories is in seeming conflict with the knowledge that the experience and event happened not in the present but within the past. This is where difference and repetition come back, as the event repeating is the sensation that we connect with the past, and its crystallization is the creation and realization of the difference. Through this, the Crystal-Image represents this split in time and allows us to not see films like we often do, as images that have come before, but also one that moves beyond those images to transform into a world of its own. We see this conjunction of the virtual and the real here in the quote:</h4>
<br />
<br />
<blockquote>“Subjectivity is never ours, it is time, that is the soul or the spirit, the virtual. The actual is always objective, but the virtual is subjective: it was initially the affect, that which we experience in time; then time itself, pure virtuality which divides itself in two as affector and affected, ‘the affection of self by self as definition of time.” (Deleuze 82, The Time-Image)</blockquote>
<br />
<h4>To further apply this confusing conversation to a more realistic sense, one can understand the Crystal-Image through the tension between time and illusion. These images come through remembering, dreams, fantasy, allegory, or even déjà vu. In the world of film, Deleuze solidifies his understanding of this illusion as a creation that splits the time of the present, future, and past. This manipulation and play on time allows for the new aspects of film, ones that Deleuze called for with the publishing of this book, to come to life and form a new reality. We will look at a personal favorite film that articulates this well: <i><a href="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2021/arrival/">Arrival</a></i> (2016).</h4>
<hr />
</h2></h6>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking into Cinema I and, mainly, Cinema II.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Screenwriting Story</title><link href="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/screenwriting-festival/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Screenwriting Story" /><published>2022-07-22T19:23:54+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T19:23:54+00:00</updated><id>https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/screenwriting-festival</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lgsump.github.io/blog/2022/screenwriting-festival/"><![CDATA[<h4>As someone who almost always stays within the realms of the humanities and strictly philosophy, I often forget that when I am in engagement with art, it is almost always in such an abstract, distant interaction. As a writer, my control and distance from my work is obviously much closer, but even then, there seems to be some abstraction in the control I have for it. When writing screenplays, I am thinking about my work in the same ways that I think about art in general as a philosopher, there isn't just an off-switch to become a practicing-only, anti-theory artist. As much as, ironically, I would like to be that in theory, there is something unappealing about disregarding the ideas and values that make the art of writing so powerful in order to truly live it.
  <br />
  <br />
  <h4>For example, this week I went to a screenwriting festival and sat through workshop after workshop, lecture after lecture, telling me all of the practical how-to's as a screenwriter. The first lecture was on what a story was, and the lecturer gave us a strict guideline of how the protaginist needs to have a goal and has to have a hard time getting there. I mean, this line to me, from a conceptual point of view, was so narrow and completely leaves out so many storys that could have real meaning. It seemed more like he was a talking point for a specific school of cinema rather than telling us what a story really was. Nonetheless, I went through the festival, learning about how to pitch, what a logline was, and, despite what they wanted, wrote a good amount of my story during the breaks! But really, I didlearn a good amount of practical lessons about the world of screenwriting, and even some gossip about the program itself and some grad students (Marcy, you shouldn't have asked that grad student for a letter of rec, she wasn't a fan!) Despite my mindset going in, you would think that would be a great help to someone like me who is constantly stuck in my work because I either give up, mid-way, because it is not going perfectly, and someone who is writing concepts and scripts for the screen but has no resources or connections to taking them anywhere further than just that, words on a screen. Part of me likes it that way, as I've heard, many times, that my writing isn't the best. The one thing that has kept me from really caring about that criticism and working on it is the fact that it is always followed up with the compliment of my concepts, analysis, and ideas. The thing I hate the most about writing, and why writing, for me, is more of a personal hobby rather than a skill I like to share is that it isn't a conversation.
  <br />
    <br />
  <h4>Writing, say posts like these, or essays for class, are never really about the engagement with the material, analysis of what someone is saying, or anything close to that. Sure, you might end up actually saying something meaningful, but the whole purpose is to become an efficient communicator <i>through one-ended writing</i>. I mean, sure, in the 1700s-1900s, the only way for scholars or professionals to engage with a large amount of ideas from people not around them, was through these open-ended, static papers that they would probably just put in one of those journals. I do think that there is some benefit for this, as it does increase or at least create a platform for looking at ideas, but the irony is probably most people reading it know the author personally. 
    <br />
    <br />
    <h4>I guess what I'm trying to say is that, as an academic and a creative writer, it has allowed me to see the beauty, bureaucracy, and out-datedness in both practical senses of creative writing like how a "story", according to that lecturer is supposed to go, or how in academic writing, in order to tell each other ideas we are still writing papers! Part of why I am so interested in becoming a professor or academic, as well as my devotion to the virtual world, is because I am so tired of how the modern experience of art has become so narrow and structured as if it had been beheaded from what it started with and is pumped with paper every now-and-then and called living.

</h4></h4></h4></h4>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My experience at a screenwriting festival and the internal conversation it inspired.]]></summary></entry></feed>